Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is nun
hey נ"ה. nun hey. We pick up four lines down from the
top of nun hey amud alef נ"ה עמוד א'. nun hey amud
alef. It's a new perek פרק, perek, the discussion right now is
focusing, it's hard to sort of always get a sense how it's
moving from one topic to the next, but the discussion anyway now
is about not the status of the woman as a niddah נידה,
niddah, but it starts with the question about the blood that comes
out, the menstrual blood that makes her a niddah נידה, niddah, that
that blood is also a source of tumah טומאה tumah for someone
who touches it. And then we're moving on to other types of
things which are source of tumah טומאה tumah with the question about
when they're moist and does it even include to when they are
dry. The mishna משנה mishna only said that the only two that
remain a source of tumah טומאה tumah even if they are dried
out is the blood of a niddah נידה niddah and the flesh
from a mes מת. mes. Other things only when they're moist not
when they're dry. The Gemara גמרא Gemara is looking at each of
these things that were mentioned and first proving how we know that
they're tamei טמא tamei and then how we know that they're tamei
טמא tamei in what state. Let's take a look now, four lines
from the top: basar hames בשר המת basar hames which is the
second thing, the only other thing that is mentioned in the mishna
משנה mishna that is tamei טמא tamei even when it is dried
up. Minalan מנלן, Minalan, where do you know that the flesh of
a dead body is tamei טמא? tamei? I mean the Torah תורה,
Torah, the simple sense of the Torah תורה Torah talks about the
entirety of the dead body; if a person touches it or is
under the same roof of it. Resh Lakish amar kra ריש לקיש
אמר קרא, Resh Lakish amar kra, the verse says, L'chol tumato לכל
טומאתו, L'chol tumato, so this that this is the law for dead
body for all of its impurities. L'chol tumoat haporash mimenu לכל טומאות
הפורש ממנו, L'chol tumoat haporash mimenu, all things that separate from it
are also the source of tumah טומאה. tumah. Rabbi Yochanan amar רבי
יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar o b'etzem adam o b'kaver או בעצם
אדם או בקבר o b'etzem adam o b'kaver now
if you touch the bone of a person or a grave, Adam
dumya d'etzem אדם דומיא דעצם, Adam dumya d'etzem, so it says etzem
adam עצם אדם, etzem adam, the bone of a man, so a
bone is like the man. Mah etzem yavesh af kan yavesh מה
עצם יבש אף כאן יבש, Mah etzem yavesh af kan yavesh, so
the same way a bone is tamei טמא tamei even dry, even
here tamei טמא tamei even dry. So here actually, although before and
later the Gemara גמרא Gemara will try to as I said prove
that the thing is itself tamei טמא, tamei,
here the Gemara גמרא Gemara is immediately moving into assuming that the
flesh is tamei טמא tamei and trying to prove how you know
that it is tamei טמא tamei whether moist or dry. So the
Resh Lakish's ריש לקיש Resh Lakish's drasha דרשה drasha was not just
to tell you that anything that separates from it is also tamei
טמא, tamei, that the flesh is tamei טמא, tamei, but also that
it's always tamei טמא tamei like l'chol tumato לכל טומאתו l'chol tumato
under all of its tumot טומאות, tumot, so when whatever state that
flesh is in, the things of a dead body are tamei טמא
tamei even if they are dried up. And Resh Lakish ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish says no we learn it out from the comparison to
a bone. And the same way a bone is dried and tamei
טמא, tamei, therefore any parts of a mes מת mes even if
they are dried up are also tamei טמא. tamei. Now the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says mai beinaihu מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what difference does
it make if you learn it out from the word l'chol לכל
l'chol or whether you learn it out from the comparison to the
bone. Ika beinaihu d'afri aprichei איכא בינייהו דאפרי אפרוכי Ika beinaihu d'afri
aprichei that it basically can crumble. It is so dried up that
it can crumble. On the one hand that in the verse of
l'chol tumato לכל טומאתו, l'chol tumato, all of its tumah טומאה tumah
it's very inclusive, but it's not similar to a bone; a bone
is dry but it's not going to crumble upon touch. So if
that's dried up then it would not be tamei טמא tamei if
that is your drasha דרשה. drasha. Maseivei מיתיבי, Maseivei, I'll ask you
on this we have a mishna משנה mishna in Ohalot אהלות Ohalot
that says basar hames shehuphrach בשר המת שהופרך, basar hames shehuphrach, if
you have the flesh of a corpse that it literally can be
huphrach הופרך huphrach basically means if you snap it it'll dissolve, that
has completely disintegrated, tahor טהור, tahor, it's tahor טהור, tahor, so there
you see that it does matter if it's dry beyond a certain
point it is no longer tamei טמא. tamei. The Gemara גמרא Gemara
says hasam d'ikmach v'havei afra התם דאיקמח והוי עפרא, hasam d'ikmach v'havei
afra, that's not just that it will crumble but that actually is
that it completely has disintegrated and it's like dust. So basically saying
if it's disintegrated like dust everybody agrees that it's not even considered
to be flesh anymore. If it's normally dried up everybody considers that
that's tamei טמא. tamei. The question is
that it can crumble but it's not it'll shatter; it's so dry
that it will shatter but it's not going to turn into dust.
On the one hand it's not like a bone and therefore if
that's your drasha דרשה drasha it would not be tamei טמא, tamei,
but on the other hand it should be included in the verse
l'chol tumato לכל טומאתו, l'chol tumato, that is the difference where we
learn it from. Okay so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like
this, Maseivei מיתיבי, Maseivei, kol shebames metamei כל שבמת מטמא, kol shebames
metamei, everything in a dead body causes tumah טומאה tumah every part
of a dead body chutz min hashinayim v'hase'ar v'hatzipporen חוץ מן השיניים
והשיער והציפורן chutz min hashinayim v'hase'ar v'hatzipporen with the exception of teeth,
hair, and fingernails, u'vish'at chiburan hakol tamei ובשעת חיבורן הכל טמא u'vish'at
chiburan hakol tamei and if those are attached to the dead body
then they are tamei טמא, tamei, but separated they are not. Okay,
so the question is what makes these three things special? The Gemara
so the assumption here is that they're special because in some ways
they are not
like bone meaning if you say like Resh Lakish ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish l'chol tumato לכל טומאתו l'chol tumato all of the things so
the same way that tells you whatever state it's in whether fresh
or dried. It's also be totally inclusive and it should include things
like teeth and fingernails and bones. If, however, you say the דרשה
drasha of עצם אדם, etzem adam, then it's more limiting, you know,
the flesh, bones, blood, but we don't assume everything. So basically it's
a question about whether you assume like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish לכל
טומאתו, lechol tumato, a completely inclusive category, and then you have to
argue why to exclude things. So we had to argue that if
it completely dissolves, then it's completely like something different. But otherwise our
fundamental position is everything is included. So why are these things excluded?
I can't remember offhand. Take a look. You have the חומש Chumash
in front of you. Okay. So then, anyway, so here we have.
So why are these things, if you base it on you need
to include something, so fine, you could say these things aren't exactly
like bone, these things aren't like flesh, they're not like blood, they
wouldn't be included. According to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, everything is included.
Why are these things excluded? So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, דומיא דעצם.
dumya de-etzem. So it does have to be like the bone, presumably
even according to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
Okay, so דומיא דעצם. dumya de-etzem. מה עצם שנברא עמו אף כל
שנברא עמו, Ma etzem she-nivra imo af kol she-nivra imo, that the
same way bone is created with a person, so therefore the only
things that are טמא tamei are parts of a body that are
created with you. But your teeth are not created with you. So
says, okay fine, that solves the teeth problem. But the גמרא Gemara
says והאיכא שיער וציפורן, ve-ha-ika se'ar ve-tziporen, how about hair and fingernails?
You are created with those. So you can't exclude those based on
bone. שנבראו עמו וטהורין, she-nivru imo ve-tehorin, they are created with you
and they're טהורין. tehorin. אלא אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Ela amar
Rav Adda bar Ahava, דומיא דעצם. dumya de-etzem. Here's the way we
compare it to a bone. מה עצם שנברא עמו ואין גיזו מחליף,
Ma etzem she-nivra imo ve-ein gizo machlif, the same way a bone
is created with
you and also its trunk does not replace itself. That by the
way is a phrase that is used, you know, also by like
whether you make a ברכה bracha בורא פרי העץ Borei pri ha-etz
or בורא פרי האדמה. Borei pri ha-adamah. What type of thing, whether
it's, you know, whether the trunk sort of remains from year to
year or it has to regrow from year to year, which is
like why ironically, right, you make a בורא פרי האדמה Borei pri
ha-adamah on like bananas, right? Why are they, I mean they grow
from a tree, but the point is, but the tree dies and
regrows every year, that's גיזו מחליף. gizo machlif. Passion fruit trees. Yeah.
And it's crazy, they're so tall, right? And they totally die out
and totally regrow every year. Anyway, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says
that here too, that's the principle.
Where were we? ואין גיזו מחליף. ve-ein gizo machlif.
So here, in order for something to be considered similar to a
bone and similar to a מת, meit, it number one has to
be created with a person
and as opposed to hair and fingernails, although they're created with a
person, if you would cut fingernails or cut hair, they would just
regrow. So therefore they're not considered to be as intrinsic to the
dead body. And you understand the logic, right? Things that aren't created
with a person aren't as intrinsic or things that will fall off
and regrow aren't as intrinsic. So those things are not considered to
be a source of טומאה. tumah. שיער וציפורן שנבראו עמו וטהורין אלא
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Se'ar ve-tziporen she-nivru imo ve-tehorin ela amar
Rav Adda bar Ahava, דומיא דעצם. dumya de-etzem. מה עצם שנברא עמו
ואין גיזו מחליף. Ma etzem she-nivra imo ve-ein gizo machlif.
Bone number one are created with you and number two, if you
lose a bone it doesn't replace itself. אף כל שנברא עמו ואין
גיזו מחליף. Af kol she-nivra imo ve-ein gizo machlif. So all, so
in order for something to be considered intrinsic, it has to be
created with you and it does not replace itself. יצאו שיניים שלא
נבראו עמו, Yatz'u shinayim she-lo nivru imo, teeth weren't created with a
person. יצאו שיער וציפורן, Yatz'u se'ar ve-tziporen, hair and fingernails, שאף על
פי שנבראו עמו, she-af al pi she-nivru imo, גיזו מחליף, gizo machlif,
they replace themselves.
How do fingernails replace, I mean you
cut your fingernails, they'll regrow.
I understand that, but like, but that's not usual. Let's say you
cut like a little piece of skin off, that's also.
We'll ask that. Okay. So anyway, so those are things that are
not intrinsic and therefore they are not טמא. tamei. Okay, so one
minute.
Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on,
so even ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who says that we learn that
a very inclusive verse from לכל טומאתו, lechol tumato, whatever state the
part of the corpse is in, he agrees at least to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that we learn from bone to limit what types
of the body, what parts of the body are טמא. tamei. And
everybody learns from bone that that limits it and it has to
be like bone, it has to be created with the person and
it does not replace itself, and only those parts of the body
cause טומאה. tumah. And that everybody agrees is what we learn from
bone. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says like this.
Okay, והרי
עור, ve-harei or,
how about this skin? דגיזו מחליף, de-gizo machlif, that if you,
this is more or less what Michael was asking, if you know,
you get a little cut, your skin will replace itself, will grow
back. So עור or does,
you're like the outer layer of skin, right, not the flesh, the
skin. ותנן, ve-tenan, and הגלודא, ha-gluda, רבי מאיר מכשיר וחכמים פוסלין, Rabbi
Meir machshir ve-Chachamim poslin, and this is like ודתנן ve-ditnan
and I'll show you that skin replaces itself because. As we've, not
from evidence but from a משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, because the משנה Mishnah
*Mishna* says that if you have an animal that has its skin
removed, is it a טריפה treifah *treifa* or not, completely been like
flayed alive. So Rabbi Meir says it's kosher, it's not a טריפה
treifah, *treifa* because it'll heal and it won't die, and the rabbis
say it's invalid, which is a funny phrase but it means that
it's a טריפה *treifa*. So, okay, the rabbis say it's invalid, presumably
that means the skin won't grow back. But no, now we're going
to say ואפילו רבנן לא קפסלו *veafillu rabanan lo kapaslu* even the
rabbis only invalidate, say it's a טריפה *treifa* אלא דאדהכי והכי שלטא
ביה אוירא *ela deadehachi vehachi shalta beih avira* because by the time
it takes for the skin to grow back the animal would be
exposed, the flesh will be exposed to the elements ומיית *umait* and
it'll die as a result but that doesn't mean the skin won't
grow back ולעולם דמחלף *uleolam demachlif* the skin will grow back. So
presumably we can infer from this debate if we frame the debate
that way that everybody agrees that the skin will grow back. So
that's number one what we see by skin by an animal, presumably
it's the same by a human, and nevertheless ותנינא *vetanina* אלו שעורותיהן
כבשרן *eilu sheoroteihen kivasran*
and we have a משנה Mishnah *Mishna* that says the following: the
skin is like the flesh. עור האדם *or haadam* the skin of
a human, that the same way the flesh of a human corpse
causes טומאה tumah *tumah*, the skin of a human corpse causes טומאה
tumah *tumah*. So why is this? We've already established from a משנה
Mishnah *Mishna* by animals and טריפות treifot, *treifot* that skin grows back
and Michael said you can just know it from your experience and
we said that the skin is טמא tamei. *tamei* like flesh. Why
is that? Why don't we say something that grows back is not
טמא tamei. *tamei*? How is it different than hair and fingernails? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. האי איתמר עלה אמר
עולא Ulla *hai itmar alah amar Ulla* so one minute, no, you
know what, technically you're right because we said on this that עולא
Ulla *Ulla* said דבר תורה Torah עור אדם טהור tahor *devar Torah
or adam tahor*. Really biblically the skin of human beings is טהור
tahor.
*tahor*. ומאי טעמא אמרו טמא tamei, *umai taama amru tamei*
so why do we say that the skin is טמא tamei. *tamei*?
So it says ומאי טעמא אמרו טמא tamei *umai taama amru tamei*
גזירה שמא יעשה אדם עורות אביו ואמו שטיחין לחמור *gezeira shema yaaseh
adam orot aviv veimmo shetichin lachamor*. There's a very sort of a
shocking concern, we're afraid that a person will take the skin of
his father and mother, the skin of the bodies of relatives and
turn it into like a type of a seat for a on
a donkey. So they used it for actual leather purposes. So חס
ושלום *chas veshalom* they should do that, therefore we had to say
that they are טמא tamei *tamei*.
Of course that some of those are practice.
Yeah, you wonder what the context is for that. It's also very
obviously deeply disturbing because it makes you think about the Holocaust and
things that we've seen about what they did with human skin.
The question also that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks is and what about
the fact that you're not allowed to derive benefit from a dead
body? Why isn't that a concern here? So תוספות *Tosafot* actually has
two answers. One is that for some people, particularly I assume for
כהנים *kohanim* or people that were just very מחמיר *machmir* in טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'tahara, *tumah vetaharah* sometimes we find that laws of טומאה
tumah *tumah* were greater concern than other prohibitions. Like for example the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, I think in the end of פסחים *Pesachim*
if I remember correctly,
that they said that פיגול *pigul* was טמא tamei *tamei* of a
קרבן korban, *korban* because that's way they would get כהנים *kohanim* to
avoid making פיגול *pigul*. The fact that they would be over on
biblical prohibitions by making it eating פיגול *pigul* wasn't enough, but because
the rabbis made it טמא tamei *tamei*, טומאה tumah. *tumah* was something
they stepped away from, which is fascinating, which shows that we know
exactly we know that psychology nowadays that people they have taboos around
things that are not always reflective of the actual weight of the
prohibition. The other answer תוספות *Tosafot* says is that maybe it's not
איסורי הנאה *issurei hanaah*, gets to a question about the same way
we have a question of what's considered an intrinsic part of the
body for the sources of טומאה tumah. *tumah*, you have a similar
question of what's considered part of the body for the prohibition of
deriving benefit. And he has a discussion that maybe the skin is
not included in that. So it seems to be a very strange
concern and I agree with Dov that maybe there is some other
context there seems to have been some other context here, but nevertheless
he says technically you're right, it is טהור tahor, *tahor* because it
replaces itself it's טהור tahor? *tahor* and we're only treating it as
טמא tamei *tamei* as a protective measure.
And then what about these other things?
Like what other things? What would be? Oh that you'll make those
into what, the hair and whatever. Oh you're concerned that you'll make
the hair of a dead body into a pillow or something. Yeah
I don't know but that's right. There has to be some context
why we're particularly concerned about this. Yes hair actually continues to grow
after somebody's dead, right? And fingernails as well? Fingernails as well, oh
so maybe that's a reason. Something the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says but
that could be an interesting reason that those are excluded. Yes that
they have life even independent of the yeah.
Making wigs out of hair of a dead person.
Yeah
I would I would agree it would seem to me that hair,
use of hair is a much greater concern than use of the
skin. It's easier to remove, it's not whatever, it would just seem
to me yeah it's funny that that was not a concern.
Okay.
Okay so now the גמרא haGemara, *Gemara* says like this where were
we?
Okay. איכא דאמרי *ika deamri* some have this going the other way
that the version is like this: הרי עור דלא מחליף *harei or
dela machlif*. The גמרא haGemara *Gemara* starts by saying not that assuming
that skin does replace itself, skin doesn't replace itself. How do you
know that? דתנן וחכמים פוסלין *detnan vechachamim poslin*. We're going to infer
from The fact that the rabbis say that a flayed בהמה behemah,
is a טריפה is because they're assuming that it does not replace
itself. And that's the reason why the rabbis say it's a טריפה,
not because it takes time to heal, but because it does not
heal, it doesn't replace itself. ואפילו רבי מאיר לא קמחמיר ve'afillu Rabbi
Meir lo kamachmir and even Rabbi Meir who says that it's not
a problem of flayed בהמה, behemah אלא דקרי בשרא וחייא ela dekari
bisra vechaya
because basically the flesh will become hardened and will protect it. So
he doesn't really believe that the skin will grow back. He just
believes that the flesh will somehow, you know, toughen and serve to
keep the animal alive. ולעולם אין גלדו מחליף, ule'olam ein gildo machlif,
but the skin really doesn't grow back. So now that we've established
the skin doesn't grow back, why is that a problem? We've just
said it's טהור tahor. because ואמר עולא... ve'amar Ulla... I'm sorry, I'm
sorry, because we've said it's טמא. tamei So right, the משנה Mishnah
says that the skin is טמא. tamei So now the problem is
not on the משנה haMishna that says that the skin is טמא,
tamei it's on עולא's Ulla statement. ואמר עולא דבר תורה עור אדם
טהור. ve'amar Ulla devar Torah or adam tahor. But now we have
a problem because עולא Ulla says that really biblically speaking, you know,
the real law is that this the skin is טהור. tahor So
now the question is the other way. עולא Ulla says that fundamentally
the skin is טהור, tahor, it's only a rabbinic concern. But now
we're arguing that the skin doesn't grow back, so biblically you should
be טמא. tamei So how come עולא Ulla is saying that the
skin is טהור? tahor גמרא gemara says כי איתמר דעולא אסיפא איתמר.
ki itmar deUlla asseifa itmar. No, עולא's Ulla statement was said on
the end of this משנה haMishna that spoke about the different types
of skins that are טמא tamei or טהור. tahor? That this משנה
Mishna. said that like the skin of a human is טמא tamei,
and all the other types of things that are טמא tamei, and
then it ends by saying וכולן שעבדן או שהלך בהן, vekulan she'ibadan
o shehilach bahen,
even those types of things that the skin is טמא tamei? including
humans, if you were to actually process them or walk on them,
you know, which is a way to turn them into a leather
as you take the skin and you actually go through a processing
of making it into leather. כדי עבודה kedei avodah or you walk
on them the amount of time it takes to actually process it,
טהורין tehorin the משנה says then they are טהור tahor. because now
they've been sort of, you know, they've changed their identity, they're now
leather. חוץ מעור אדם chutz me'or adam with the exception of human
skin. So actually this context makes a lot more sense, עולא's Ulla
statement, because it explicitly singles out human skin and it says you
process this and turned it into leather and everything no longer has
the דין din of skin and is no longer טמא tamei with
the exception of human skin. Now עולא Ulla clarifies, and here we
understand we're in the context of having turned skin into leather. דאמר
עולא דבר תורה עור אדם כי עבדו טהור. de'amar Ulla devar Torah
or adam ki ibdo tahor. You know what, human skin fundamentally has
the same הלכה halachah that not automatically it's טהור, tahor, no, normally
it's טמא tamei. like we said because it doesn't replace itself. But
if you've processed it and made it into leather, then it's טהור
tahor. just like everything else. ומה טעם אמרו, u'mah ta'am ameru, why
did they say that if it's made into leather it's not it's
not טהור? tahor. גזרה שמא יעשה אדם עור אביו ואמו שטיחין gezeirah
shema ya'aseh adam or aviv ve'immo shetichin that we're afraid God forbid
a person will use his father and mother's skin and turn it
into leather and actually make it into some type of a, you
know, of a of a seat for a donkey. So this context
of עולא's statement, again, you don't know why specifically, you know, Ulla's
singling out skin as opposed to other things but at least we're
talking in a context where it's explicitly describing a scenario where the
person turns the skin into leather and it specifically singles out human
skin and says that doesn't help. So עולא is explaining it doesn't
help because rabbinically we don't like the idea of you turning skin
into leather and we don't want this scenario to happen, so therefore
it's not going to help but fundamentally it does. But the basic
principle is according to this version that skin is דאורייתא de'oraita a
source of טומאה tumah because it is not גלדו מחליף, gildo machlif,
it does not replace itself, which is quite fascinating that the גמרא
gemara is willing to go either way based on a debate of
a skinned בהמה behemah to say well, maybe skin does replace itself,
maybe it doesn't, depending on how we interpret this debate about a
flayed בהמה and doesn't actually ask the question about whether skin actually
does replace itself. I mean, I think it really depends on what
the scenario is. You have a little bit of a cut, right,
and it'll heal. Like if you have an actual serious amount of
skin removed from your body they have to do skin grafts, right?
So I mean a big type of a thing doesn't replace itself,
small types of things eventually do heal.
Yeah, yeah, so I remember way back about one of the rabbis
who did an experiment on a bird and put
it on the...
oh to see, right, and he actually, right, right, they
were talking about
about טריפות, not about this, about a bird without its skin, without
its feathers, without its down and its feathers, yes.
Was it only the feathers?
From what I remember, yes, I remember it was the feathers. But
it is true that that was an actual, right, that was an
actual interesting גמרא gemara that was about doing actual, you know, experimentation
in חולין, Chullin, right. חולין Chullin was an interesting מסכת masechet where
we dealt with that question about, right, exactly, where we dealt with
that question about empirical evidence and the value of empirical evidence. But
again here I guess by the skin as I said, it could
go either way depending on how much of the skin we're like
talking about. I don't know, if God forbid somebody had his entire
fingernails pulled off, would they grow back or do you need the...
he says yes, Dovi says no, maybe it may... maybe it depends
if they were pulled out by their roots or not. Like, you
know, I don't know, I have no idea. Okay, why is it
that when a larger section of skin is torn off it doesn't
grow back and a small section does?
Do you know? grow back from the edges and there's just not
enough time before it starts to heal, get stitches, yeah, to help.
Right. I see.
Okay. But what?
Why won't it just keep on... so it won't grow back a
little bit from the edges? Yeah.
But then the new edge will then go back from... you know
what I mean? Why won't it just continue to do that? It's
just...
it has to seal probably pretty quickly
or something.
Yeah. It's actually complicated. It has to do with the immune system.
There are some lower... there are some other... there are animals that
will completely regrow limbs if you cut them off. But
those...
but those are highly simplistic... so you know... well, I don't know.
All right. Anyway, fine. Let's keep on going. So now... now that
we've done with the skin, now we're going to go to the
flesh. הרי בשר דגזיה מחליף וטמא. Harei basar digzya machlif vetamei. How
about fundamental like one of the basic basic aspects of a corpse
that is טמא tamei, is the flesh? But you know if a
little bit, if you lose like a little, you know you get
a cut or something digs away and you know you lose a
little piece of your flesh, eventually it'll heal. So אמר מר בר
רב אשי בשר נעשה מקומו צלקת. Amar Mar bar Rav Ashi basar
na'asa mekomo tzaleket. Even though it grows back, still it does not
like totally heal, you will sort of see sort of like, you
know, there'll be a scar. There'll be a scar.
Healing and regeneration is different. What? Healing and regeneration is different.
Right, that's a good point.
Surface... sort of surface healing is not the same as
right, right, right, very good. So that's the basic answer of the
גמרא, Gemara that there'll be some type of healing but it will
not completely replace itself and there'll still be a scar. Okay, so
that's where we know that the parts of a body which are
טמא tamei, or not, the ones that are not or the ones
that are not as integral to it, not not grown with it
and will not replace itself. And we also learn either from the
comparison to bone or from a more inclusive פסוק pasuk that even
when it is dried up. אבל הזוב, Aval hazov, but now we
get to the list and we're going to see actually the end
of the משנה that we have the opinion of רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yose that says actually flesh of a body is like everything else,
that it only when it is moist not dried. But really, so
we have those two things that are even dried, the דם הנידה
dam hanida and the בשר המת. basar hamet. And now we have
the rest of the משנה which are things which are only when
they're moist not dried.
And we are going to, as I've said,
look at first how we know the things are טמא tamei. and
then how we know they're טמא tamei, in what state. אבל הזוב.
Aval hazov. We missed the ריש לקיש Reish Lakish or רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan debate, right? The debate? Right. Okay. אבל הזוב, Aval hazov,
right. אבל הזוב, Aval hazov, so now
we have the actual...
the flow of a man that causes him to be a זב,
zav, a certain type of a flow, not שכבת זרע. shichvat zera.
So זובו מנלן? zovo minalan? How do we know that the flow
itself, not just the man is a זב, zav, but how do
we know that the flow itself makes him is טמא, tamei, the
same way we asked how we know the blood of a נידה
nida is, not makes him, is a source of טומאה tumah for
other people who touch it? The same way we asked the question
of the blood of a נידה. nida. It makes him or her
טמא, tamei. but how do we know that when they experience it,
but how do we know that the touching it by another person
makes that person טמא? tamei, דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא:
Beraisa: זובו, zovo, this shall be it, it says וזאת תהיה טומאתו
בזובו, vezot tihye tumato bzovo, this is his טומאה tumah in his
flow,
טמא הוא, tamei hu, so טמא tamei, is it... okay that was
not זובו טמא zovo tamei is a different פסוק. pasuk. What is
it? וכי יזוב? vechi yazov? No. וזאת תהיה טומאתו בזובו רר בשרו
את זובו או החתים בשרו מזובו טומאתו היא, vezot tihye tumato bzovo
rar besaro et zovo o hechtim besaro mizovo tumato hi, I think
it says, או החתים בשרו
מזובו טומאתו היא, o hechtim besaro mizovo tumato hi, anyway. So there's
one פסוק. pasuk. You have it there? Sorry. Here.
איש איש כי
יהיה זב מבשרו זובו
טמא
הוא.
Ish ish ki
yihye zav mibsaro
zovo tamei
hu.
Okay, very good. Okay, what is it? 15:2. All right, thanks. דברו
אל בני ישראל ואמרתם אליהם איש
איש כי יהיה זב מבשרו
זובו טמא הוא.
dabru el bnei yisrael veamartem
aleihem ish
ish ki yihye zav mibsaro
zovo tamei hu. So his flow, זובו טמא הוא, zovo tamei hu,
so his flow טמא הוא tamei hu is his טמא. tamei So
that actually seems, you know, it could be he is טמא, tamei.
but not that reading the פסוק pasuk is that his flow is
also טמא, tamei, זובו טמא. zovo tamei. ומי מנלן זוב שהוא טמא?
Umi minalan zov shehu tamei? The flow itself is טמא. tamei. So
now the ברייתא Beraisa says: והלא דין הוא, vahalo din hu,
I could learn that out from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, who
needs a
פסוק? pasuk? לאחרים גורם טומאה, leacherim gorem tumah, if it makes
others... meaning others is the man who experienced it, because the whole
question is that others who touch it. If it makes others, if
it makes the person who experienced it טמא, tamei, so certainly it
itself should be a source of טומאה. tumah If it makes the
person an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, certainly it itself is an אב
הטומאה. av hatumah. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, right? No, שעיר
המשתלח יוכיח. seir hamishtaleach yochiach. How about the goat that is sent
off over the cliff, שגורם טומאה לאחרים, shegorem tumah leacherim, the person
who pushes it off the cliff is טמא, tamei והוא עצמו טהור,
vehu atzmo tahor,
and it itself is טהור. tahor. So right, if somebody were to
just touch the goat, you'd be טהור, tahor. but the person who
sends it off the cliff is טמא. tamei So here too, the
man who experiences the flow could be טמא, tamei but
the flow itself. it causes him to be טמא, הוא tamei hu
עצמו טהור, tahor the thing in itself maybe is טהור. tahor If
you experienced it, you're טמא tamei. because you're a זב, zav, but
the thing itself is not itself טמא. tamei, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
so therefore you needed the verse, זובו טמא, zovo tamei, his flow
is טמא, tamei, לימד על הזוב שהוא טמא, limed al hazov shehu
tamei, that actually the flow itself, not just the man who experienced
it, that the actual flow itself is itself טמא. tamei. ואימא, ve'eima,
okay so all you know it's טמא, tamei how do you know
how טמא tamei. it is? הני מילי במגע, hani mili bemaga, it
may be if you touch it, אבל במשא לא, aval bemasa lo,
if you carry it not. Now if somebody carries a זב zav
even without touching the זב, zav, you're טמא tamei. by carrying him.
So the argument here is going to be that this is טמא
tamei? as the זב zav himself. So how do we know that?
Maybe it's just טמא. tamei It says it's טמא, tamei maybe minimum
טומאה. tumah If you touch it you're טמא, tamei not if you
carry it. מידי דהוה אשרץ, midi dehavah asheretz, we have things like
that, שרץ sheretz is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, but the only
way they communicate טומאה tumah, is through touch, like a dead rodent.
So maybe this is in the lowest category. אמר רב ביבי בר
אביי, amar rav bibi bar abaye, במגע לא איצטריך קרא, bemaga lo
itztrich kra,
you don't need a פסוק pasuk about touch, דלא גרע משכבת זרע,
delo gara mishichvat zera, it's no worse than semen. Okay, now we
know for example that the first time a זב zav has a
flow, although it's not a seminal flow, his טומאה tumah is the
same as a בעל קרי, baal keri, right? A זב zav when
he has two flows, he's a זב zav seven days, three flows
he brings a קרבן, one flow, although the thing that's flowing from
him is not semen, his status is like a בעל קרי, baal
keri, he has טומאה tumah of one day. So it says, and
by the semen the Torah is explicit that the semen is טמא.
tamei. It speaks about the semen touching other things. So it says
we would know that he is at least in the category at
least as bad as semen. So therefore, because if it happens two
or three times it makes him even more טמא tamei. and once
it makes him like a בעל קרי. baal keri. So therefore we
know, we just figure out from the comparison or analogy here that
it's at that it's like semen and if you touch it you're
טמא. tamei. So therefore you didn't need a פסוק pasuk to tell
you that. כי איצטריך קרא למשא, ki itztrich kra lemasa, if the
פסוק pasuk is going further to say טמא tamei הוא is going
to give it a greater, a weightier טומאה tumah, to say even
if you carry it. So the Gemara says fine, ואימא במשא מטמא
אדם ובגדים, ve'eima bemasa metamei adam uvegadim, במגע אדם מטמא בגדים לא
מטמא. bemaga adam metamei begadim lo metamei. Maybe I should say the
following: when you carry it, it makes you and your clothes טמא.
tamei. Right? Remember the general הלכה halacha is is that we're talking
about a thing, whatever it is, the flow here, the זוב, zov,
that is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. What's the story of an
אב הטומאה? av hatumah? It makes a person who touches it become
a ראשון, rishon, clothes that touch it become a ראשון, rishon, food,
everything that touches it becomes a ראשון. rishon. Now if a person
now goes who's
a ראשון, rishon, what can a ראשון rishon make טמא? tamei Only
food. Only food can be a שני. sheni. So if I go
ahead and I touch something and I'm a ראשון rishon and then
I touch clothes, they're actually טהור. tahor, All right? I haven't done
anything to them. However because you're wearing, there's some טומאות tumot where
if I touch it or carry it, I'm טמא tamei and not
only that the clothes that I'm wearing is טמא tamei, and not
only is the clothes and they're טמא tamei as a ראשון. rishon.
That we view me and the clothes that I'm wearing as one
unit. And when I touch or carry certain types of טומאות, tumot,
we all become a ראשון, rishon, even though my clothes did not
directly touch it. So that's not what you would normally say. Normally
you'd say I'm a ראשון rishon and my clothes get off the
hook because they're touching me and they don't become a שני, sheni,
but there's sometimes we consider me a unit. Okay, but that depends
on what is the טומאה tumah, and how am I touching it.
So that's what the Gemara is saying right now. Fine, it's another
level of טומאה, tumah, but there are some טומאות tumot like we're
going to see like a נבילה, neveilah, a corpse of an animal,
that if I touch it my clothes are טהור. tahor, Only if
I carry it are I and my clothes seen as one unit
and טמא. tamei. Maybe this should be the same. So let's take
a read. But a מת, meis, other types of things, like for
example if I touch a זב zav or a נידה niddah or
a מת, meis, other types of things, even by touching, me and
my clothes are טמא. tamei, Okay, so what?
פרה
אדומה, parah
adumah, right, the one who does the עבודה avodah of the פרה
אדומה, parah adumah, correct, but here we're talking about sort of the
touching versus carrying, there it's also more about being עוסק osek in
sort of actually doing the process. But you're right, that's true as
well. Okay, so there are basically the following levels. There's some types
of things like a שרץ sheretz where your clothes on you are
never טמא. tamei There are other types of things like a נבילה
neveilah where when you carry it your clothes are טמא tamei, but
not when you touch it. And then there are other types of
things like a זב zav and a זבה zavah and a נידה
niddah and a מת meis that even when you touch it your
clothes are טמא. tamei, So we have to move this up the
levels. A, how do we know it's not like a שרץ? sheretz?
Maybe carrying it you're טהור. tahor, No, we already knew it was
like שכבת זרע, shichvat zera, the extra פסוק pasuk tells you it's
more strict. Okay, more strict, but maybe only your clothes are טמא
tamei when you carry it, which is category number two. How do
we know that your clothes are טמא tamei. even when you touch
it, which is category number three? That's going to be the question.
So let's take a look. ואימא במשא מטמא אדם ובגדים, ve'eima bemasa
metamei adam uvegadim, when you carry it you and your clothes are
טמא, tamei, במגע bemaga if you touch it, אדם מטמא בגדים לא
מטמא, adam metamei begadim lo metamei, you are טמא tamei. but your
clothes are not טמא. tamei Now where do you have something in
that category? מידי דהוה אמגע נבילה, midi dehavah amaga neveilah, like by
touching a corpse of an
animal. have an animal, if you carry it, your clothes are טמא
tamei *tamei*, but if you touch it, only you. How do you
know to put this in the highest category that even when you
touch it your clothes are טמא tamei *tamei*? גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
לא סלקא דעתך *lo salka dach* it does not make sense that
it's in category two because דתניא detanya, *d'tanya* we learn in a
ברייתא braita *Braita* אחרים אומרים *Acherim omrim* others say הזב את זובו
לזכר ולנקבה *Hazav et zovo lizachar u'lnekeivah*. This is the law for
the the the the one with the who flows his flow male
or female. So מקיש זובו לו *makish zovo lo* it says הזב
את זובו *Hazav et zovo* the flower and his of his flow.
So his flow is connected to him. מה הוא לא חלקת בין
מגעו למשאו לטמא אדם ולטמא בגדים *Mah hu lo chilakta bein maug'o
l'massa'o l'tamei adam u'ltamei begadim* the same way by the זב zav.
*Zav* himself whether you touch the זב zav, *Zav* or carry the
זב zav *Zav* you and your clothes are טמא tamei *tamei*. So
if that's true אף זובו כן *af zovo kein* so the same
is true by the flow. Basically it's just as טמא tamei *tamei*
as he is. So the same way when somebody touches or carries
a זב zav *Zav* both the person and the clothes are טמא
tamei. *tamei*. The flow as well is in the highest category even
if you just touch it you and your clothes are טמא tamei
*tamei*.
Okay so wait so the first פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* is doing what?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is kind of saying. והשתא
דנפקא לן מהזב את זובו *V'hashta d'nafka lan m'Hazav et zovo* so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay great so now you learned
out that the flow is טמא tamei. *tamei* from this פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* that it compared the flow to the זב zav, *Zav*. So
זובו טמא tamei למה לי *Zovo tamei lamah li* who needed the
first פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* that we have on the עמוד א׳ *amud
aleph* that said his flow is טמא tamei? *tamei*? Here it says
that your flow is like you. So who needs the other פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*? אמר רב amar Rav יהודה מדסקרתא *Amar Rav Yehuda midiskarta*
so said רב יהודה מדסקרתא *Rav Yehuda midiskarta* אצטריך *itztrich* you still
need both פסוקים psukim. *psukim*. סלקא דעתך אמינא salka datach amina, *salka
dach amina* if I just had the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* הזב את
זובו *Hazav et zovo* I would not have said that the flow
is טמא tamei. *tamei*. Why not? I would have said שעיר המשתלח
יוכיח שגורם טומאה tumah. לאחרים והוא עצמו טהור tahor, *Sa'ir Ha'mishtaleach yochiach
she'goreim tumah l'acherim v'hu atzmo tahor* that I would not have started
with an assumption that your flow is going to be טמא tamei.
*tamei*. I would say we have cases where something makes you טמא
tamei. *tamei* but it is טהור tahor *tahor* like the goat right
that gets sent over the cliff. So maybe the flow makes you
טמא tamei. *tamei* and it is טהור tahor *tahor*. So what do
you do with the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* of הזב את זובו *Hazav
et zovo* that connects flow to the person? ואי משום הזב את
זובו למניינא הוא דאתא *V'ee mishum Hazav et zovo l'minyana hu d'ata*
that's not to tell you that your flow is טמא tamei *tamei*.
That's to have extra words of flow in order to tell you
how many flows you need in order to become a זב zav
*Zav* a full זב zav *Zav* that needs seven days of טהרה
tahara *tahara*. We had this once before. What does that mean? זוב
חד זובו תרתי הזב *Zov chad zovo tartei Hazav* one flow את
זובו *et zovo* two flows right and then so two flows you're
a זב zav. *Zav* and you have a seven days. And then
it says לזכר ולנקבה *l'zachar u'lnekeivah* male or female. So by the
time you get to up to for two flows you have the
category of a male but ובשלישי *u'v'shlishi* when we're talking finally about
the third flow because we say ולנקבה *v'lnekeivah* אקשי רחמנא לנקבה *akshi
Rachmana l'nekeivah* then it's like a female. What does that mean? If
you remember one of the big differences is that between male and
female by זב zav. *Zav* and זבה zavah, *Zavah* that זבה zavah
*Zavah* needs three days but male needs three seeings even without three
days but a female the flow is even if it's באונס *b'oness*.
By a זב zav *Zav* only if the flow is not due
to external causes. However that's the first two that makes him into
a זב zav, *Zav*. The third flow that means he has to
bring a קרבן *korban* that's even if it's אונס *oness*. How do
we know that? Because the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says והזב את זובו
*v'hazav et zovo* two לזכר *l'zachar* for the first two you're in
the male category only if it's not due to external categories ולנקבה
*v'lnekeivah* and then there's a third stage where it's even like the
female even due to external causes the third flow that you bring
a קרבן *korban*. That's the דרשה derasha. *drasha* from that. The basic
upshot of all of that being is that I would not have
said this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is coming to tell you the status
of the flow as a source of טומאה tumah. *tumah*. I would
say the whole פסוק pasuk *pasuk* here is coming to teach you
the idea about how many times you see and whether it has
to be whether you're טמא tamei *tamei* because of אונס *oness* or
even not because of אונס *oness*. Okay because I would have said
I don't know to begin with an idea that your flow is
טמא tamei *tamei*. I can't infer it from the fact that you're
טמא tamei. *tamei*. I have no basis to say the flow is
טמא tamei, *tamei*. This whole פסוק pasuk *pasuk* I would have said
is about determining how many flows you need. So therefore כתב רחמנא
זובו טמא tamei. *katav Rachmana zovo tamei*. Then so the explicit פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* tells me זובו טמא tamei. *zovo tamei* your flow is
טמא tamei *tamei*. Now that I know your flow is טמא tamei,
*tamei* I go back to this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* הזב את זובו
*Hazav et zovo* to tell me that it also understands the degree
of טומאה tumah, *tumah*. It compares the flow to you. Now that
I know the flow is טמא tamei *tamei* and it's being compared
to you then I'll say it's just as טמא tamei? *tamei* as
you are. והשתא דאמר רחמנא זובו טמא tamei הוא דרש ביה נמי
האי *v'hashta d'amar Rachmana zovo tamei hu darsh bei nami hai*. Now
I have to learn out both things. I can learn out how
many types of flow how many times you need a flow and
whether they're באונס *b'oness* or not. But the fact that it says
הזב את זובו *Hazav et zovo* phrased that way it also tells
me that it's as טמא tamei, *tamei* as the זב zav *Zav*
himself. Okay so that's where we know it from. We know that
it is טמא tamei. *tamei*. We know that it is the that
it is the highest level of טומאה tuma, *tumah* because it is
compared to him. Interestingly we do not have a דרשה *drasha* here
to tell me only when it's moist as opposed to dried up.
Presumably that's the assumption. It's described as flow. So if it's flow
it has to be in a liquid state. And unless we have
a פסוק *pasuk* that teaches us otherwise we will say that if
it's dried up it's not considered flow and it is not a
source of טומאה tuma *tumah*. So that is the the actual flow
of זב *Zav*. But then the משנה *Mishnah* continues and it says
והניצוץ *v'hanitzotz*. והניע והרוק, veharok. the sort of phlegm and the spit
of a זב. You'll remember that we also say that other types
of מעיינות, mayanot, wellsprings of a זב, not all fluids but certain
fluids that are basically what the גמרא Gemara says מתעגל ויוצא mit'agel
veyotzei that collect in the body and then come up like phlegm
and spit and so on, that these things are also an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, not just a ראשון rishon but they're an אב
av just like... so sweat wouldn't be and these things, right, and
these things are also only when they are sort of in a
liquid state, not when they are in a dried-up state. So the
גמרא says והרוק. So רוק מנא לן, rok mina lan, where do
you know that רוק rok is itself a source of טומאה tuma.
and then we'll get to the other issue about moist versus dry,
דתניא, detanya, וכי ירק הזב בטהור. vechi yarok hazav batahor. So that
actually is explicit in the פסוק, like the פסוק speaks about spitting.
It says what, did I? Or what...
I don't know why. Brand new
tape, sorry about that, they don't make them like they used to.
I don't know, I guess, okay.
Okay, so where were we? I have to see, maybe I have
to keep telling it that you're... anyway, it says like this, so
where's the פסוק? וכל הנוגע... וכי ירק הזב בטהור וכבס בגדיו ורחץ
במים וטמא עד הערב.
vechol hanogea... vechi yarok hazav batahor vechibes
begadav verachatz bamayim vetamei ad ha'arev. If he spits
on a טהור tahor person, the person is טמא, tamei.
which means that the spit itself has to be an אב av
because a person touched the spit. The only way a person could
become טמא tamei is if he touches an אב, av, so you
see that the spit is an אב. av. Okay, so דתניא, וכי
ירק. vechi yarok. יכול אף על פי שלא נגע, yachol af al
pi shelo naga, that is if he spits on a טהור tahor
person, maybe just the act of spitting, maybe not the spit itself,
right? So the act of a זב spitting at you, maybe even
if the spit doesn't touch you, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar בטהור, batahor,
on the טהור, tahor. so somehow it indicates that it actually hit
the טהור, tahor עד שיגע בטהור, ad sheyiga batahor, it has to
touch him. אין לי אלא רוקו, ein li ela roko, now I
only know that the spit is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. כיחו
וניעו ומי האף שלו מנין, keicho venio umei ha'af shelo minayin,
how do I know about the כיחו וניעו? keicho venio? רש"י Rashi
says that they're different types of phlegm, so he suggests one is
something that comes out through like a deep cough and the other
is something more from like a surface cough, but whatever, different types
of phlegm and what do you call it? Mucus, not mucus, green
nose.
I know,
but what the stuff in my nose is called mucus, is it?
Yeah, it is. Okay, I thought there was a more specific term
for the... okay anyway. ומי האף שלו מנין, umei ha'af shelo minayin,
where do you know? So תלמוד לומר וכי ירק. talmud lomar vechi
yarok. So the extra somehow ו', vav, וכי ירק vechi yarok is
including other forms of liquid that are like spit and we as
before described that that is basically called מתעגל ויוצא, mit'agel veyotzei, collects
and then comes out. אמר מר, amar mar, יכול אף על פי
שלא נגע, yachol af al pi shelo naga, perhaps I would say
even if it doesn't touch. Meaning what? Like just the act of
spitting would make him טמא, tamei. right. So now it's looking at
that phrase. מהיכא תיתי, meheicha teti, so how where would I have
ever thought that the act of spitting could make somebody טמא, being
spat upon not even spitting? סלקא דעתך אמינא, yeah I would have
thought to think, נלף רוק רוק מיבמה, neleaf rok rok miyevama, learn
it out from the act of יבום. yibum. So מה התם אף
על פי שלא נגע, ma hatam af al pi shelo naga, although
we said that she spits, you know, לפניו lefanav in his presence
and it doesn't have to touch him and that's somehow a significant
act, הכא נמי דלא נגע, hacha nami dlo naga, maybe here too
it's the act of being spat upon that makes you טמא without
it touching you. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so it tells
us בטהור. batahor. So the גמרא says ואימא הני מילי במגע, veaima
hani mili bemaga, okay fine, so now you've proven that spit is
טמא. So now we're going to go through the same point, but
it just says טמא, it doesn't say how טמא. So there are
three levels: טמא only by touch not by carrying,
maybe only your clothes are טמא only when you carry it, and
then the third level is that even your clothes are טמא even
when you touch it. So we're going to have to prove how
you go up all three levels. ואימא הני מילי במגע, veaima hani
mili bemaga, maybe the spit is only טמא if you touch it,
because that's anyway the case that the spit hit the person, אבל
במשא לא, aval bemassa lo, but not by being carried, מידי דהוה
אשרץ, midei dehavei asheretz, just like a dead rodent, it's only causes
טומאה by touch not by being carried. אמר ריש לקיש תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל, amar Reish Lakish tana dbei Rabbi Yishmael, we learn out
from רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, אמר קרא בטהור, amar kra batahor, he
spits on the טהור, tahor so we read בטהור batahor not meaning
it hit the טהור, tahor, which we read before to say it
has to touch you, but here בטהור, batahor, מה שביד
טהור, ma shebeyad tahor, even if it just hits something that the
טהור tahor, is holding. So it's not somehow it spits ב', ba,
I don't know exactly how he gets it from that prefix, not
prefix, that preposition, on something that is ב' ba something that is
in the טהור's tahor, hand, in the טהור's tahor, possession, ב' be
somehow but not actually hitting the טהור tahor, himself. So you're holding
a stick and the spit hits the stick, you're טמא even though
it didn't hit you because now you're carrying the stick. מה שביד
טהור, ma shebeyad tahor, so something even in the hand of the
טהור. tahor טימאתי לך, timeti lach, that I have made טמא. So
there we see even carrying. Okay, that gets us up to level
two, but ואימא במשא מטמא אדם ובגדים, veaima bemassa metamei adam uvgadim,
maybe because it does say that your clothes are טמא as well,
that's what it says, וכי ירק הזב בטהור וכבס בגדיו. vechi yarok
hazav batahor vechibes begadav. So maybe fine, if you're carrying it, you
and your clothes are טמא. במגע bemaga במגע אדם לטמא ובגדים לא
לטמא, b'maga adam l'tamei u'vigadim lo l'tamei,
but if you're touching it, only you and not your clothes, מידי
דהוי המגע נבילה, midi d'havei hamaga n'veila, like if you touch a
נבילה n'veila that only you are טמא and not your clothes. How
do I know it's level three, that even by just touching it,
both you and your clothes are טמא? אמר ריש לקיש משום תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל אמר קרא בטהור. amar Reish Lakish mishum tana d'vei
Rabbi Yishmael amar kra batahor. Again, בטהור, batahor, which until now we've
learned that three things. One is it has to touch you. Number
two is even if it doesn't touch you, even if you're carrying
it, but it's not enough just to be spat upon, it has
to touch you or you have to carry it. And now we're
saying the fact that it says
בטהור, batahor, טהרה שהטהרתי לך במקום אחר טמאתי לך כאן, tahara she-hittarti
lach b'makom acher tameiti lach kan, that even here that it's something
that I would have said elsewhere you are טהור tahor. about, meaning
that I would have said that your clothes are טהור tahor. if
you would have just touched something, here I am saying
you are טמא.
Yeah. So the גמרא says ואיזה זה מגע נבילה. v'eizeh zeh maga
n'veila. That is touching a dead a corpse of an animal that
normally I would say your clothes are טהור, but here somehow בטהור
batahor is learning to say the opposite of טהור, right, it's spat
upon a טהור, something that otherwise would be a טהור, here you're
going to be טמא. So what does that mean? It means that
even the touching of a נבילה, n'veila, even the touching of it
will make your clothes
טמא. ואימא במשא דשרץ. v'eima b'masa d'sharetz. No, maybe it's just telling
you what we said until now, that if you carry it you're
טמא. Normally and it's more strict than like a rodent. A rodent
you're only טמא if you touch. Here you're טמא even if you
carry. So yes, we're making it more strict than other cases, but
how do you know to make it the most strict? So the
גמרא says no, אם כן נכתב קרא באדם. im ken nichtav kra
b'adam. Remember the ב bet already tells us you're טמא by carrying
it. There's somehow the ב bet tells us even if it doesn't
touch you, even if it's something you're holding. So if it just
wanted to say that it would say וכי ירוק הזב באדם, v'chi
yarok hazav b'adam, on a person, which means the ב bet we're
learning to tell you even if it doesn't touch you, even if
you're carrying it. And that would have already gotten you into category
number two. The fact that instead of saying באדם b'adam we say
בטהור batahor
is somehow telling us something that otherwise would have been טהור, even
if you touch it, your even your clothes are going to be
טמא. מאי בטהור שמע מינה תרתי. mai batahor shma mina tarti. Okay,
so we did just like we did before. We went up the
ladder and we said it tells you you're טמא, but based on
various דרשות, drashot, here interestingly when it came to the actual flow,
it was by comparing the flow to the זב himself. Here when
it came to the other types of fluids, it wasn't a direct
comparison to the זב, but by various דרשות drashot going up the
ladder to say that it is the highest source of טומאה, it
is an אב av that even touching it makes you and your
clothes טמא. We don't have an actual פסוק to tell me only
when it's moist, but again it's being described as spit. So we
assume without a פסוק otherwise, only when it is moist, not when
it is dried out. And now we'll use the rest of today
to discuss the question about what fluids and the different categories of
the fluids.
Can I just have a question about the יבמה? yevamah? Why are
we assuming that she's טמאה? tmeiah? If she's טהורה? tehorah?
No, we're not assuming she's טמאה. tmeiah. No, no, no, no, it's
just saying that here's a case where the תורה Torah describes an
act of spitting that doesn't require hitting anybody.
But it doesn't say וירקה בפניו. v'yarka b'fanav.
בפניו. b'fanav.
So she she does have to hit.
No, it just has to be in front of him. Now תוספות
just say once we learn out that the spitting of a זב
has to hit him, maybe we should go back and make the
same argument by יבמה. yevamah. But for now we'll take for granted
that it says בפניו, b'fanav, in his presence, it doesn't necessarily hit
him.
If she's טהורה tehorah then it doesn't matter.
Right. We're not saying that she causes טומאה, we're just saying the
תורה Torah describes an act of spitting. So maybe the same way
other places an act of spitting even has nothing to do with
laws of טומאה וטהרה, to say to spit on someone doesn't mean
you actually hit them with your spit. It just means you spat
towards them in their direction in front of them. So here too
when it comes to טומאה, totally different case, but since it describes
an act of spitting, maybe it'll also just spitting at somebody without
necessarily hitting them. So we're not saying that it's the same הלכה.
halacha. There it has nothing to do with טומאה. We're trying to
describe when the תורה talks about the act of spitting, does it
assume that the spit hits somebody or not? That's the only question.
Is it also when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol throws the blood
onto the...
Yeah, oh that's a similar point that it doesn't have to hit.
Right. It doesn't have to. It's not right. Right. It would... but
that's the same point. It's towards that, but without necessarily hitting. Correct.
Okay, so now we're going to look at other types of fluid.
So what we mentioned spit and we mentioned phlegm and we also
mentioned mucus.
Well mucus is in the ברייתא but it's not actually in the
משנה.
I know, which is what the גמרא is going to discuss. ומי
האף, u'mei ha-af, so mucus. מאי מי האף, mai mei ha-af, what
does that mean? אמר רב ובלבד no, we know what mucus is,
but it means what's the circumstances? אמר רב בניגרר דרך הפה, b'nigrar
derech ha-peh, it means that you spit out the mucus through your
mouth, right? Sometimes that happens, especially if you have a cold with
like a what is it, nasal drip or something. Anyway, that you...
so the you know, it goes through your nasal cavities into your
mouth and you spit it out through your mouth. That's the case.
לפי שאי אפשר למי האף בלא צחצוחי הרוק, lefi she-ee efshar l'mei
ha-af b'lo tzichtzuchei ha-rok, because really mucus is not a source of
טומאה. It's really... but when the mucus comes out of your
mouth.
No, even if it comes out through your nose, that actually mucus
is a source of one of the מעינות. mayanot. So here's a
fundamental debate whether mucus is one of the מעינות mayanot of a
זב or not. And it's not exactly clear why not. It certainly
falls into the category of מתעגל ויוצא, mit'agel v'yotzei, it collects and
then comes out. Maybe it has to do with the fact that
it's less, you know, it's more viscous, it's sort of less, you
know, fluid. I have no idea why it should, what makes it
not similar to the others. But we'll take a look, maybe just
has to do with the דרשה. So anyway, that's the debate, whether
it fundamentally is a מעיין mayan or not. So, רבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו וניגרן דרך החוטם. Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu v'nigran derech hachotem. אלמא
קסבר מעיין הוא. Alma kasavar mayan hu. So he said that it
is a real, it is itself a מעיין, mayan, it is itself
a source of טומאה, ורחמנא רבייה, v'rachmana rabyay, and it's included in
the פסוק. ורב נחשב נמי דמעת עינו. V'Rav nachshev nami dimat einu.
So, so one minute, but Rav, who is saying that we're talking
about when it goes through your mouth, so why doesn't Rav also
mention eye tears? Now, what does that mean? Because we're going to
see that Rav understands that your tears, your tears can come through
your nose. I don't think that's true, right? You have tear ducts
in your eyes and they directly produce the tears, right? It's not
the same type of thing. Anyway, but how do we know this?
דאמר רב De'amar Rav because Rav says, האי מאן דבעי ליסתמיא לעיניה,
hai man d'ba'i listmiah le'einei, if you want to go blind, here's
some advice I have for you. Sounds like a Jewish grandmother, right?
Okay, if you want to go blind, ליכחול מעובדי כוכבים, lichol me'ovdei
kochavim, go ahead and get a non-Jew to give a medicinal treatment
to your eyes. This כיחול kichul was some very type of medicinal
treatment they had for eyesight and anyway the point was that this
reflects the assumptions in מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah which were
some of the realities at the time of occupation by the Romans,
at least some time, was, you know, that they're looking for an
opportunity to kill... the non-Jews were looking for an opportunity to kill
the Jews. So therefore you cannot do anything that sort of puts
you in their hands. So Rav says if you go ahead and
try to get this medicinal eye treatment from them, they're going to
put some poison in it and they'll blind you, or at least
it's a concern. So he phrases it in this way, here's what
you can do to go blind. ולוי אמר, V'Levi amar, Levi says,
האי מאן דבעי למימות, hai man d'ba'i lemut, if you want to
die, ליכחול מעובדי כוכבים, lichol me'ovdei kochavim, go get this treatment because
the poison would go through your eyes and will actually kill you.
ואמר רב חייא בר גוריא, V'amar Rav Chiya bar Guryas, מאי טעמא
דרב, mai ta'ama d'Rav,
why did Rav not say like Levi, that this is a good
thing to do if you want to die? Meaning, how come he
only thinks it'll make you blind? הואיל ויכול לגורנו ולהוציאן דרך הפה
Hovil v'yachol l'goranu u'lhotzi'an derech hapeh
because you could sort of, you know, pull it out, go or
whatever it is, you know, take... I don't know how you would
do it with the eyes but anyway, do some type of, you
know, thing to get the poison and spit it out. So the
same way you could like spit out if, you know, venom if
you got a snake bite, you could somehow spit this out through
your mouth. It would still go through your eyes so it would
blind you but it wouldn't kill you because you could get it
out of your body. So you see Rav thinks that the tears
and things that go in the eyes can come out through your
mouth. So
the גמרא says: ורב נהי דזהירי נפיק דמעתו גופא לא נפיק. V'Rav
nehi d'zhiri nafik dimato gufah lo nafik. No, Rav would say poison,
stuff inserted through your eyes, you could somehow pull out through your
mouth, but actually the tears themselves will not be able to come
out through the mouth. So that's why Rav did not mention tears
because he does not believe that the tears can actually go through
the mouth, but as we know, the mucus from the nose can.
Okay.
But so does Rabbi Yochanan think that the tears...
We have no idea what Rabbi Yochanan thinks about that. We know
what Rav thinks and since Rav thinks that anything that goes to
the mouth has spit in it, we wanted to know why he
didn't mention tears. And it says because he doesn't think that you
can pull tears through your mouth.
Such a strange assumption because tears are associated with sniffles. With what?
Tears are associated with crying.
Oh with crying, with sniffles, aha, interest, maybe, maybe.
Okay, so anyway, alright. So now though, that's one question, but if
it goes through your mouth that we're concerned about, we're concerned about
spit is reasonable. But now we have to worry about whether the
what do you call it, the actual mucus itself is considered a
מעיין mayan and the גמרא does not actually explain what that debate
is really about. Now we're going to take a look though, we'll
continue the discussion about a classic here quote about the different categories
of fluids of a זב. So let's take a look: תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear, תשעה משקין הזב, tisha mashkin hazav, there
are nine fluids of a זב. They're not all in the same
category, there's going to be three, three and three.
הזיעה, Haze'a, sweat, והליחה סרוחה v'haleicha serucha which is like a, you
know, sort of rancid,
literally like rancid liquid, I'm not exactly sure what it is. And
והרעי, v'hare'i, and what is it? What kind of liquid? Yeah, I
don't... does any of your translations...
Koren calls it pus.
Pus, oh that's interesting. That makes sense. Okay, that makes sense, right?
And ליחה leicha is sometimes referred to as pus. Okay, so that
makes sense, pus and and what do you call it, bowel movements,
right, והרעי, v'hare'i, which could also be, you know, more fluid depending
on if a person has diarrhea or something. All of those, not
urine, טהורין מכלום. tehorin miklum. Those are completely טהור because they are
שאינן מעיינות, she'einan mayanot, they are not things that collect. and can
come out and liquidy. And number two is that
that they are not considered liquids altogether. They're never—the idea of drinking
or liquids are never associated—I mean they they might be in a
liquid state, but in no הלכה halacha are they considered liquids. Okay,
דמעת עינו dimat eino tears, ודם אגפתו v'dam agpato and blood from
a wound, וחלב v'chalav and milk of a woman who is a
זבה, וחלב אשה v'chalav isha מטמאין טומאת משקין ברביעית. metamin tumas mashkin
birvii. Those things are considered liquids, so the fact that a זב
touched them or the זבה makes them a ראשון rishon as though
as similar if they touched any sort of liquids, but they are
not actually the מעיינות ma'ayanot because these are things that are not
considered מתעגל ויוצא, mitagel v'yotzei, they don't collect and come out. I
mean you understand that, right? Tears are come out right away, blood
comes right out, it doesn't collect in a certain area, milk actually,
right, it's you know it's the act of a nursing causes the
lactation. Is that—no, that's not true though, right? Doesn't doesn't a woman's—even
if it's not the
baby,
she
still—and not—but not only that, right? Even before then, and she goes
a while without nursing, her breasts fill with milk. Right. Right. So
I wonder why milk is not included, why that's not מתעגל ויוצא
mitagel v'yotzei like the other stuff. Maybe it doesn't come out by
itself? I don't know. But it doesn't? Yeah. I don't know exactly
why milk not. All right, something to think about. So those—those are
considered fluids, but not מעיינות ma'ayanot and therefore they are ראשון. rishon.
And if there's a רביעית, reviit, a minimum amount like three and
a half ounces, then they're
טמא. אבל זובו, aval zovo, but the actual flow itself for a
male זב, רוקו, roko, the spit, ומי רגליו, v'mei raglav, and the
urine, those מטמאין טומאה חמורה, metamin tuma chamura, those are an אב
הטומאה, av hatuma, those are in the categories of מעיינות. ma'ayanot. Okay,
so now we have this whole nice division. What's not in this
list?
Mucus. ואילו מי האף לא קתני, v'ilu mei ha-af lo katani, it
doesn't say mucus. So בשלמא לרב לא קתני, bishelama l'Rav lo katani,
so according to Rav I understand why it's not there, דלא פסיקא
ליה למתני, d'lo psika lei l'misnei, it's not always in the—that that's
the הלכה, halacha, that's not always the
case. זימנין דאתי דרך הפה וזימנין דאתי דרך החוטם. zimnin d'asi derech
ha-peh v'zimnin d'asi derech ha-chotem.
Sometimes it comes by the mouth and sometimes it goes by the
nose. And it in itself anyway is not the source of טומאה,
it's only because it has spit mixed up with it. אלא לרבי
יוחנן ליתני, ela l'Rabbi Yochanan lisnei, according to Rabbi Yochanan it should
have mentioned mucus. So the Gemara says, ולטעמיך, u'l'taameich, and according to
your argument, כיחו וניירו מי קתני, keicho v'niyoro mi katani, it didn't
say the other thing which we have explicit in our Mishna, which
is the the phlegm. So it's not listing everything, it just didn't
say mucus, also didn't say phlegm. אלא תנא רוק וכל דאתי מריבויה,
ela tana rok v'chol d'asi meiribuiya, it says—it says spit and anything
that's learned out from the פסוק of spit.
הכא נמי תנא רוקו וכל דאתי מריבויה. hacha nami tana roko v'chol
d'asi meiribuiya. It says spit and anything that's learned from the פסוק
of spit. So phlegm and according to him also mucus are learned
from the from the פסוק about spit and therefore it does not—it
does not mention them. They are essentially subcategories. Okay, so now we're
going to just wrap this up. דמעת עינו, dimat eino, to say
the middle category. How do you know these various things but that
are not מעיינות, ma'ayanot, various things are considered to be liquids, fluids,
and therefore are a ראשון. rishon. So דמעת עינו, dimat eino, how
do you know tears are considered to be a משקה? mashke? Because
like normal people don't drink tears, normally to call something a משקה
mashke it would not only have to be in a fluid state,
but something that people drank. So דמעת עינו דכתיב, dimat eino d'chtiv,
all these things we have verses. ותשקמו בדמעות שליש, v'tashkemo bidmaos shalish,
and he made him drink, you know, of the tears. So it's
a—it's a—so this poetic פסוק is talking about drinking
tears.
שליש shalish is—King David drank his tears in תהלים. Tehillim. Oh yeah?
That's right, it was something like this some other passage.
Oh, he watered—no, he soaked his bed with his tears.
All
right, anyway—okay, well that—yeah, that was in the תחנון. Tachanun. Okay, anyway
so here we have a פסוק about drinking tears. ודם אגפתו, v'dam
agpato, how do you know blood of a wound? דכתיב ודם חללים
ישתה. d'chtiv v'dam chalalim yishteh. A lot of—a lot of poetic verses,
but since it's using the word drink by these things, that's enough
to put it in that category. So it says the blood of
corpses he will drink. So and corpses, so a wound is like
a partial corpse. מה לי כוליה מה לי פלגיה. ma li kulei
ma li palgei. What do I care if the whole person is
dead or part of him, basically it means blood of a wound.
חלב אשה, chalav isha, milk of a woman. It's pretty funny that
actually, you know, people do drink milk but they don't drink human
milk and actually it's pretty rare that we drink milk as a
beverage. You know, milk was really used for making cheese and whatever.
I mean it's—I think it's pretty recent that milk had been drunk
especially—right, cow's milk. Right. So how do you know that that's considered
to be a—to be a
liquid? ותפתח את נאוד החלב ותשקהו. vatiftach et nod ha-chalav vatashkehu. Oh,
so you have it by, you know, Sisera and and, right, so
that Yael that she made him drink from the milk. Okay, so
all those things are called—it says drinking, so even though they're not
necessarily normally drunk, they are liquids and they become a ראשון. rishon.
מי רגליו מנלן mei raglav minalan and now the final thing is
we've learned רוק rok and subsets of רוק. rok. Sc—you know, phlegm
and mucus. How about urine? Where do we get that from?
דתניא זובו טמא וזאת. d'tanya zovo tamei v'zot. It says—it says his
flow is טמא and then it says וזאת תהיה טומאתו v'zot tihiyeh
tumato and this will be
his impurity. The other thing that comes from that area, which is
the urine.
לרבות מי רגליו לטומאה L'rabos maymi raglav l'tuma even the urine. Okay.
ולא דין הוא? V'lo din hu? I could have made it from
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה רוק הבא ממקום טהרה טמא u'ma
roke habah mimkom tahara tamei the spit that comes from a טהרה
place, your mouth is
טמא, מי רגליו הבא ממקום טמא אינו דין שיהיו טמאים? maymi raglav
habah mimkom tamei eino din sheyiyu tmeim? The urine that comes from
a טמא place, why טמא? Not because of an attitude towards sex,
but טמא only in the sense that the flow, the penile flow
is טמא, so fundamentally that's where the טומאה of a זב comes
from. So how much obviously the urine should be טמא. So אינו
דין שיהיו טמאים? eino din sheyiyu tmeim?
So גמרא says not necessarily. דם היוצא מפי האמה יוכיח. Dama hayotzei
mipi ha'ama yochiach. How about if there's blood coming from that from
the penis? שבא ממקום טמא וטהור. Sheba mimkom tamei v'tahor. That comes
from the same place and it's טהור. Not everything that comes from
there is טמא. אף אתה אל תתמה על זה שאף על פי
שבא ממקום טומאה יהא טהור. Af ata al titmah al zeh she'af
al pi sheba mimkom tuma yehei tahor. Maybe urine although it comes
from there should be טהור. Maybe it's not as bad as spit.
Just because it comes from there doesn't prove anything.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, זובו טמא וזאת. zavo tamei v'zos. His flow
is טמא and this. לרבות מי רגליו לטומאה L'rabos maymi raglav l'tuma
that even the urine is טמא. So you see here by the
way, although we normally refer to
מתעגל ויוצא, mitagel v'yotzei, here it's learning it from specific פסוקים. א
פסוק A pasuk that tells you things similar to spit, א פסוק
a pasuk to tell you urine. So the issue about the mucus
might not be that conceptually it's the same category, but at the
end of the day, maybe you need א פסוק a pasuk and
maybe it's not so much about a conceptual category as what פסוק
puts things into the same category as sources of טומאה.